<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='../tools/mosa-rfc-transform.xsl'?>

<rfc xmlns='http://www.mosa.org/schemas/mosa-rfc.xsd'>

  <header>
    <title>MOSA License Affilliation</title>
    <abstract>This specification provides a means for MOSA members to allow other MOSA members to use or port, and relicense certain portions of code.</abstract>
    <number>0002</number>
    <status>Proposal</status>
    <type>Informational</type>
    <sig>Standards</sig>
    <dependencies/>
    <supersedes/>
    <supersededby/>
    <author>
      <firstname>Jonathan</firstname>
      <surname>Dickinson</surname>
      <org>Ensemble</org>
    </author>
    <revision>
      <version>0.0.1</version>
      <date>2008-05-23T00:00:00.0000000+00:00</date>
      <initials>jcd</initials>
      <remark>
        <p>First draft.</p>
      </remark>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <version>0.0.2</version>
      <date>2008-05-28T00:00:00.0000000+00:00</date>
      <initials>jcd</initials>
      <remark>
        <p>Ammended a problem where projects could remove the header and cause legal issues.</p>
      </remark>
    </revision>
    <conformanceterms used='true'/>
  </header>

  <section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
    <p>
      Bodies within MOSA may wish to license their code in such a way that it may be (one or more of):
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>Ported</li>
      <li>Used directly</li>
      <li>Dynamically Linked</li>
      <li>Statically Linked</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      In such a way that all of the following conditions are met:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>The license may be changed to the new project's license of choice</li>
      <li>Recognition will be given to all authors</li>
      <li>Applicable changes are submitted to the original project</li>
    </ul>
  </section1>
    
  <section1 topic='Business Rules' anchor='rules'>
    <p>
      A project that wants to share code should add this code header to applicable files. This header
      MUST be placed below an OSI-approved license header.
    </p>
    <code caption='MOSA License Header'>
      /* This project is affiliated with MOSA (Managed Operating Systems Alliance).
       * Please see the mosalicense.txt for information on the license.
       *
       * If this file is copied place relevant information at the end of the authors 
       * section below according to the format:
       * &lt; First Name &gt; &lt; Family Name &gt;:
       *   &lt; Project &gt; - &lt; License Name &gt;
       *
       * Authors:
       */
    </code>
    <p>
      The following file MUST be included in the repository in an obvious location,
      and MUST not be modified unless this document is ammended.
    </p>
    <code caption='mosalicense.txt'>
      This project is affiliated with MOSA (Managed Operating Systems Alliance).
      Other projects within MOSA may code files within this code repository that
      have the MOSA license header. They are allowed to use the files containing
      the header in the following ways:
      
      o Port it directly to another programming language,
      o Use it directly,
      o Compile against it in a dynamically linked fashion,
      o Compile against it in a statically linked fashion,

      without the former licensing provided that they:

      o Only append author, project and licensing information to the header.
      o Provide feedback and patches to the original project (for any portable
        changes).
      o Place the header in their code, below their license agreement.
      o Place a new OSI-approved license header in the code file.
        o This license must idemnify all contributors to the code from all
          liabilities.
      
      This exception is bound to the specific version of the file, that version of that
      file is known as affiliated. If the header is removed from the affiliated file, 
      the new version of the file becomes known as removed. All projects that use
      the affiliated file may continue to do so: but are not required to submit
      updates to the originating project. If the originating project re-adds the
      header to the removed file and wishes to obtain updates it must inform all the 
      other projects within MOSA of this action.
      
      Destination projects will not be held responsible for not providing updates
      to a previously removed file if they were not made aware that it became affiliated
      once again.
    </code>
  </section1>
    
  <section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
    <p>Futher consideration must be given to the legalities of the process.</p>
  </section1>
</rfc>
